# Raluca-Maria Sandu

I am currently finishing my PhD Degree in Biomedical Engineering, previously having graduated with an MSc in the same field and a BSc in Control Engineering and Applied Informatics. My research interests are machine learning, computer vision, statistics, and robotics applied in the med-tech field.

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of Bern, ARTORG Center for Biomedical Engineering

PhD in Biomedical Engineering

MAY 2017 - FEB 2021

My project was part of a European Innovative Training Network (HiperNav) funded through a Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant.

Thesis: "Quantitative assessment of ablation treatments for liver tumours – image-based efficacy analysis and predictive modelling".

## **RWTH Aachen University, Faculty of Medicine**

MSc in Biomedical Engineering

OCT 2014 - MAR 2017

Thesis: "Image Segmentation and Semantic Description: Tools and

Analytics" conducted at Philips Research Eindhoven, NL

Thesis Project Grade: 100%; GPA: 83%

#### **POLITEHNICA University of Bucharest**

BSc in Control Eng. and Applied Informatics

OCT 2010 - JUL 2014

Thesis: "Volumetric Capnography Respiratory Signals for Spontaneously Breathing Subjects" in collaboration with Philips Research Eindhoven, NL Thesis Project Grade: 98%; GPA: 83%

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Philips Research Eindhoven, Personal Care and Wellness Department

*Research & Development Graduate Student* JUL 2016 – MAR 2017 (9 months)

- ✓ Designed and developed a web-based application for image annotation
- ✓ Applied image processing techniques and machine learning algorithms for classification and semantic segmentation of skin surface structures

Research & Development Intern

APR 2016 – JUN 2016 (3 months)

✓ Utilized image processing techniques to extract features that measure the influence of skin appearance of various diets followed by subjects

#### Helmholtz-Institute for Biomedical Engineering, RWTH Aachen

Student Research Assistant

JAN 2016 - MARCH 2016 (3 months)

✓ Signal processing of cardiac signals to optimize ventricular assist devices

### Joint Research Centre for Computational Biomedicine, RWTH Aachen

Student Research Assistant

NOV 2014 – JUL 2015 (9 months)

✓ Analysed interactions between cancer cell lines using MATLAB

#### Philips Research Eindhoven, Personal Health Department

Research & Development Intern

JUL 2013 - OCT 2013 (4 months)

✓ Used signal processing methods and extracted physiological features from respiratory signals of healthy and diseased patients

Research & Development Intern

JUL 2012 – SEP 2012 (3 months)

✓ Implemented data mining techniques for analysis of physiological signals of chronic heart failure patients' part of telemonitoring study

#### **CONTACT**

E-mail: raluca.sandu@rwth-aachen.de

Website: raluca-san.github.io
GitHub: github.com/raluca-san

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/rmsandu

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- ✓ Data Science
- ✓ Machine Learning
- ✓ Python (numpy, scikit-learn, pandas, matplotlib, seaborn)
- ✓ R (Ismeans, lme4, ggplot2)
- ✓ MATLAB
- ✓ Git (GitHub, Bitbucket)
- ✓ Bash, Linux
- ✓ HTML, CSS, JavaScript
- ✓ Django Web Framework
- ✓ SQL
- ✓ C/C++/C# (OOP)
- ✓ Graphic Design (InkScape, Gimp)
- ✓ Scientific Writing

#### **SOFT SKILLS**

- ✓ Resourcefulness
- ✓ Empathy
- ✓ Independent Learner
- ✓ Communication
- ✓ Positive Reinforcement
- ✓ Public Speaking

#### **LANGUAGES**

**English:** Fluent (C1)

**German:** Intermediate (B2) **French:** Intermediate (B1)

Romanian: Native

#### RESEARCH OUTPUT

#### **Peer-Reviewed Journal Publications**

- ✓ Frontiers in Oncology, Cancer Imaging and Image-directed Interventions, JAN 2021 "Volumetric Quantitative Ablation Margins for Assessment of Ablation Completeness in Thermal Ablation of Liver Tumours" (R.M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, R. Sznitman, S. Weber, P. Tinguely)
- ✓ IEEE Open Journal of Engineering in Medicine and Biology, FEB 2020 "Ultrasound based planning and navigation for non-anatomical liver resections — an ex-vivo study." (I. Paolucci, **R.M. Sandu**, L. Sahli, G.A. Prevost, D. Candinas, A. Lachenmayer)

#### **Book Chapter**

✓ Liver Pathology, Intechopen, OCT 2019

"Stereotactic Image-Guidance for Ablation of Malignant Liver Tumors." (I. Paolucci, R.M. Sandu, P. Tinguely, S. Weber, A. Lachenmayer)

#### **Conference Publications**

- ✓ IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBS) International Student Conference, NOV 2019, Magdeburg (Germany)
  - "Quantitative Volumetric Assessment of CT-guided Ablation Treatments for Colorectal Liver" (**R.M.** Sandu, I. Paolucci, J. Freedman, P. Tinguely, S. Weber)
- ✓ 31st Conference of the international Society for Medical Innovation and Technology (iSMIT), OCT 2019, Heilbronn (Germany)
  - "Quantitative Volumetric Assessment of Percutaneous Ablation Treatments for Colorectal Liver Metastases." (R.M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, J. Freedman, P. Tinguely, S. Weber)
- ✓ CURAC 18th Annual Meeting of the German Society for Computer- and Robot-Assisted Surgery, SEP 2019, Reutligen (Germany)
  - "Quantitative volumetric assessment of percutaneous image-guided microwave ablations for colorectal liver metastases" (R.M. Sandu, I. Paolucci, J. Freedman, P. Tinguely, S. Weber)
- ✓ CURAC 17th Annual Meeting of the German Society for Computer- and Robot-Assisted Surgery SEP 2018, Leipzig (Germany)
  - "A Framework for The Quantitative Assessment of Image-guided Percutaneous Ablation of Hepatic Lesions" (R. Hrabuska, **R.M. Sandu,** I. Paolucci, S. Weber)

### **Public Speaking/Conference Talks**

- ✓ ECALSS Congress (European Computer Assisted Liver Surgery Society), OCT 2019 "Quantitative ablation – Methodology and Results from the MAVERRIC Study" (Conference Talk)
- ✓ Maurice E. Müller Memorial Event at Inselspital Bern, MAR 2018 "Minimally Invasive Treatment of Liver Tumours" (Invited Speaker)

#### LANGUAGE CERTIFICATES

- ✓ German Language classes undertaken at the University of Bern until B2.2 level, (2017-2019)
- ✓ Zertifikat Niveau B1, Sprachenzentrum der RWTH Aachen, score 95%, SEP 2015
- ✓ Certificate in Advanced English CAE, University of Cambridge ESOL, grade A, JUN 2009
- ✓ Diplôme d'études en langue française DELF B1, score 80%, FEB 2009

### **EXTRACURRICULAR CERTIFICATES**

- ✓ Good Clinical Practice (GCP) Certificate, CTU Bern, FEB 2019 Clinical Investigators I: Basic GCP & clinical research training Course
- ✓ Erasmus Mobility Placement Grant for Internship at Philips Research Netherlands, JUN 2012
- ✓ Artificial Intelligence Course in partnership with Stanford School of Engineering, DEC 2011 Completed in the top 25% of the class with a score of 95.1%.

#### **HOBBIES**

- ✓ Volunteering
  - Vice-President Local Committee IAESTE Bern, Switzerland (<a href="https://www.iaeste.ch/en/">https://www.iaeste.ch/en/</a>)
- ✓ Hiking, Skiing, Snowboarding, Surfing